Well, are we live?
Hello everyone! Welcome to the
WordPress Accessibility Day 2020.
My name is Roberto Remedios.
I'm a user experience and
user interface designer.
I live in San José, Costa Rica.
I'm also an accessibility advocate.
I've been working in Latin America
with accessibility
with different groups of people:
deaf people, blind people, and
I mean, I love to share
with all you guys tonight.
I forgot to thanks on the last talk
to our sponsors, to our organizers, and
to my moderator, Kevin,
who is pasting the questions that
you guys had on YouTube into the page.
Please remember, if you have any questions,
just put the questions on the YouTube chat.
Our next speaker is Susanna Laurin,
and she will be talking about accessibility
by default in authoring tools.
She is Chief Research and
Innovation Officer at Funka.
She has more than 20 years of
experience working with accessibility
at the senior management level.
She is an international expert
on European Union accessibility
policy and regulations,
and she has did several
workshops and write some books
about the specific EN standard.
So you have the control right now, Susanna.
Thank you for joining us.
You can share your screen.
Okay. Thank you, Roberto.
I think I'm now sharing my screen
and hopefully I also have my microphone on.
[Laughing]
Is this working?
You can nod, at least.
Yes, it's working.
Okay, perfect. Thank you.
So, good morning, everyone!
I'm doing this from Sweden, Europe,
so it's very early Saturday morning
and I want to tell you straight
away that I'm not a developer.
So if you have technical
questions around my presentation
I would be happy to forward
them to our developers.
I can't get them to wake up
this early in the morning on a Saturday,
So unfortunately you will
have to live just with me.
But thank you for having me on
this marathon accessibility event.
It's exciting.
So, I can't make this work. Why?
Yeah, so just a little bit about me.
I am the Chief Research and
Innovation Officer at Funka.
I'm also the representative
of the UN initiative G3ict
and the International Association
of Accessibility Professionals
representative to the EU.
I do a lot of strategic
consulting these days,
mainly for the European Union, but also for
EU member states national governments
when they are transposing
the EU legislation into national law.
I'm leading the WADEX subgroup,
which is an expert group
helping the Commission
and the member states
implementing the Web
Accessibility Directive,
one of the recent
legislations in this area.
and I'm also one of the technical experts
in the ETSI Special Task Force 536.
and we have been responsible for
updating and harmonizing the EN standard,
which is the minimum
requirements of the legislation in Europe.
Just a couple of words on
the company I work for—Funka.
We are specialists in accessibility,
but we were founded by the
disability movement in Sweden, and we
we started as an NGO, really,
but we converted into a
private company in the year 2000.
We have our headquarters in Stockholm
and offices also in Oslo,
and Madrid, and Brussels.
We do consulting and development
on accessibility and usability.
We also do a lot of research and innovation
and that's nowadays the
department that I lead,
and so we do national projects and
also European and global projects
in research and innovation.
We also cover policy and different
kinds of studies and investigations,
and we are, of course, also
engaged in standardization,
which is extremely important
if you want to do accessibility.
Also, one of the proud founders of the
International Association
of Accessibility Professionals.
So, in Europe, the Web
Accessibility Directive
is really turning everything
upside down here.
We have been living in
a world where we have
more recommendations on accessibility
than actual regulations,
and this is now changing.
We started with a procurement directive
a couple of years ago.
Now the Web Accessibility Directive
is covering the public sector,
and in 2022 we will also have
the European Accessibility Act
which will cover products and services
in some other private sectors.
We are really moving from
recommendations to regulations.
and it's an interesting
time to be alive, here,
but we have a couple of problems
when this is happening, of course,
and one of the biggest
problems that we have
tried to solve, or looked into, at least,
is really that accessibility is much
more than a technical issue, of course,
and around 50 percent of the
accessibility problems or fails
that we encounter when we do audits,
they are created by web authors.
and this is not a surprise,
because many web authors—
and this is now in public sector mainly,
most of the web authors are not
professional communication people,
and the absolute vast majority of them
are not accessibility experts.
So, of course they do create
content that is not perfectly accessible.
and this means that we now have
approximately seven million interfaces
that are supposed to comply
with the new regulations.
and with seven million interfaces,
we have—
I don't know, I can't even
count the number of web authors
that would need training to make this work.
And, of course, that's good for us,
because we are specializing in this
and we're happy to provide training,
but it just won't scale.
It's not enough just to put out
manuals and training and, you know,
trying to make all these web
authors do the right thing,
because people change their jobs,
they get on parental leave, or, you know,
we change people all the time.
So we just need to do something
other than only training,
because that is not—will never be enough.
And that's when the idea came, that:
what if accessibility could be
built into websites from the start?
What if the authoring tools
could do something to help, here?
maybe everything can't be automized,
but at least authoring tools
should have the possibility
to give much better
support to web authors?
That was sort of the idea
behind this research project.
And we managed to lobby for this idea
and make more people interested in it,
and after a while the European Commission
came out with a call for proposals
on trying to see if authoring tools could
actually be a part of the solution here.
So, the European funding for research,
and a very common
way of doing this
is that you first, you
apply for a pilot project
where you sort of prove
that your idea or thesis is valid
and that there is something
to keep looking into.
And then, if you're
successful in your pilot,
then you can also have the possibility to
make what is called a preparatory action,
which is where you actually
perform the real research
or whatever initiative
is needed to be done.
So it's a two-step process, often.
And we did get the opportunity to have a…
to perform a pilot project
a couple of years ago
where we looked at the 30 most-used tools
in public sector bodies in the EU.
So we crawled the internet
for public sector bodies,
and found the 30 most used tools,
to make sure that we,
the efforts were made on the
most frequently used ones.
And we did some piloting and testing,
So, trying to see what happens if you,
if you're not an expert in accessibility,
and you're procuring this tool,
and maybe your supplier is also
not an expert in accessibility,
because that is the normal case — that is
the majority of these situations.
What happens then?
If you just acquire an authoring tool
and a website from
somebody that is not an expert,
how accessible is it then?
It's like, I know this is really theoretic,
because it's not really possible,
but the idea is if you just
sort of push the button
and up comes a website from your package
then how accessible is it by default?
What is built in there?
and the answer was: not much.
But we did a lot of
surveys and prototypes,
we talked to suppliers and vendors
and tool makers and so on,
try to figure out how
much is really included
in the basic standard templates, and so on.
And we did a lot of analysis
and also user testing, of course.
User testing both with web authors,
and also end users with disabilities
to make sure that the results
were valid from both perspectives.
We did also worked a lot
with different stakeholders.
this was before the corona, so we
could make physical workshops in Brussels.
We had specific workshops with web
authors from the public sector,
to see: what are the user needs?
How can the authoring
tools help these web authors
to make the right thing.
It should be easy to do the right thing
when you create content.
And we also discussed with
the end users with disabilities of course,
which are the most
common problems or fails,
or what is the biggest barrier to you?
And also looking into the
back office, so to speak.
So, If the web author has a disability,
how accessible is the actual interface
that you meet as author?
So, the back end, so to speak,
the input part of the authoring tools.
And then we also discussed with the
tool makers and other vendors, suppliers,
and also standardization bodies.
So we had a series of
workshops where we,
where we really collected user
needs and experiences
from these four different
stakeholder groups.
And the result from
this pilot was that, well,
there is not much
accessibility by default out there
in the most-used tools, unfortunately,
but there is big demand,
and also, we thought that there would be
well, a good potential to do something.
If something is not perfect, then
you have the potential to make it better.
So, the result of the pilot was
really a matrix of the most-used tools.
And also we made three sets of
guidelines for web authors,
or people who are
procuring or looking for a tool,
and also for end users with disabilities,
and for the industry.
And really this was then the
starting point for further research.
And the result of this…
from the open parts—
not everything is public
but the public parts of this project
results can be found on our website.
It's www.funka.com/we4authors.
So, “we,” and the number 4, and “authors.”
And then, of course,
the next phase started
and we were happy enough to get also
the second phase funded by the Commission.
And we are now a third
into the preparatory action,
which is called “WE4Authors Cluster.”
And, here, we work with
a cluster of tool makers,
because we think we need now to
dig deep into the real code
and the real potential of this.
So, based on the user needs that
we found in the pilot,
we are going to create new features
that can be adapted into
whatever tool you use.
We are going to do extensive user testing
to make sure that the features
that we create are really good—
they're user-friendly,
they are solving the right problems,
and that the web authors like them.
Because otherwise they won't be a success.
We are then going to try to implement
these features in different kinds of tools,
so that we make sure that we can reach
as big part of the market as possible.
And we are then, when the project is
finished, by July next year,
we are going to share code if we are
resulting in code, which I hope.
or, If we can't produce code,
then at least we will
share the documentation,
and prototypes, videos,
visits, or whatever it can be
from the user testing, to
show as inspiration others.
Because maybe everything
can't just be a snippet of code,
and then you can just implement it
quickly in whatever tool.
Maybe life is not that easy always,
so we will also describe the feature,
and describe how it works,
and what people liked with it.
So that then, the rest of the market can
hopefully use those ideas for inspiration
and also implement these ideas
in their own tools.
This is really an important part of
all European research, of course:
that the result is going to be
for the common good.
So this is not something we
or the partners will keep
behind closed doors.
The idea is really
to share it with the community.
And the members of this
cluster right now are Drupal,
we have Mike Gifford of Open Concept,
who is representing Drupal, here.
We have Plone, represented by Timo
Stollenwerk from kitconcept in Germany.
We have Sitevision, a Swedish
license-based authoring tool.
We have Joomla, and Brian Teeman
is the representative for Joomla,
and the foundation of Joomla in
Germany is also part of the project.
and we have Umbraco,
represented by Sigma in the UK.
So, these are the cluster members
who are representing different
kinds of authoring tools.
and we are, of course,
also working with other tool providers,
but we are also closely related
to the International Association
of Accessibility Professionals,
so that we can reach out
to both vendors, and also,
customers using these tools,
and the end user organizations.
So, with IAAP we have
a really broad outreach,
apart from the partners'
own networks, so to speak.
and we also work closely with ERRIN,
which is the European Regions
Research and Innovation Network.
So, in… with this network
we can also make sure that we
reach a lot of public sector bodies'
web authors in Europe
for user testing and also making
sure that the user requirements are,
are met in a really,
relevant way for them.
After the discussions with the stakeholders
and the different user groups,
and specifically, of
course, the web authors,
their needs, and also the ideas and
experiences from our cluster members,
so, to make sure that whatever
we do is sort of relevant,
and possible to use
also for the tool makers,
we have—we set up a set of criteria
for how the features would…
what kind of problems we wanted to solve,
how frequently this problem
was occurring, and so on.
And then, based on these criteria,
we selected 10 different features
that we wanted to try with users.
So now we are specifically in the position
in the project, where we are…
we have already selected 10 features,
and we are now going to
user-test them, starting in October.
So we are, right now,
finishing or refining the prototypes
that we are then going to test
in an iterative process, of course,
inviting users, web authors,
and others interested
to test the prototypes and
come back to us with feedback,
so that we can refine them and make them
better and better.
So, we have until Christmas
to do this, really,
but we're starting here in October.
So, the features that we have selected,
to try and make sure that we can
support users, web authors with,
is really how to provide alt
text—alternative text—on images.
So, the very basic thing,
but we have  seen that this is
solved in different ways,
in different authoring tools,
and sometimes it's quite hard
to make it in a good way.
and sometimes it—well, you have
the possibility to add the alt text,
but you don't get any support
on how to write it, or when to write it,
or when not, and so on.
So the whole idea here is
to provide more support.
If something can be maybe mandatory,
we will try to make it mandatory.
Alt texts can't really be mandatory,
because not all images
need them, and so on,
but we can also prompt for
the web author to do something,
so it's really visible. It's really…
you're sort of pushed
to do the right thing.
You shouldn't be—
you shouldn't have to look
for the place where to write the alt text.
It should be very obvious and sort of
“in the flow” of your authoring process.
And then, we can also provide
maybe support at different levels,
or information.
So we have all these levels
of automation we can do,
we can either build it in so that it's
really by default, making it accessible,
or we can prompt it; or we can make
information or support in other ways.
So we will try different
ways of doing this,
and see what the
web authors find most useful,
and then present that to the market,
when we have a good decision there.
So alt text is the first one,
and then we are also prototyping now the
possibility to change language
when you have multiple
languages on a website or page,
which is very common in
the European context.
We often have websites
with more than one language.
Also, we're looking at documentation
of the accessibility features,
because our research has shown that
many web authors don't really know
what their authoring tool can do.
So how can we make
the documentation better,
and also, how can we make it,
or we want to try, if it's better
to have the documentation,
that information, that
support and the research,
sort of “in context.”
So where you are actually doing something,
that is where you can
find the information.
Or, if that may be disturbing for you,
because the user experience
will then be too crowded
or too overwhelming
with all this information.
So, maybe it's better to have it sort of on
the side, that you need to go look for it.
and we have seen
different situations,
different contexts, and also
different Web author groups
who prefer one or the other,
so this will be really interesting
to do A/B testing on.
Of course, some of the really
big troublemakers in authoring
is tables and forms,
so we are going to test
supportive tables creators
and also forms editors in different way
that can…
well, a combination of making it
accessible by default
and supporting when you do
more complex tables and forms.
Of course, everything can't be automated,
or at least not now,
maybe in the future, but we want to make
sure that the author has better support,
in doing the right thing.
When it comes to video,
we are testing supporting the editor
on how to make sure that the video
is compliant with the regulations.
And then we have four features that
are sort of connected to each other,
and they all have to do with testing.
So we want to try out
how best to test accessibility
while or when you are editing
or publishing something.
So, we are trying to have
testing procedures built into the editor,
so while you're actually
creating the content.
And then another specific sort of easy win
is if we support web authors in
providing accessible documents,
specifically PDF documents.
which is all over the world,
I think, we have inaccessible documents,
and that is a big issue that
many web authors tell us
they would like to have support in.
So, some kind of testing before you, or
while you're uploading your documents,
so that you know if
the document is okay or not.
Then we want to test the full page.
So when you have
provided all the images, and the objects,
and the content that you
are going to publish,
then, during this content creation phase,
you could also test all the
different parts and objects
that you are going to publish.
So before publishing,
just check if it's accessible or not,
and then, of course, helping you to
remediate this will be an important part.
And maybe not specifically
for the Web author,
but for the website owner,
or the person who is responsible
for the whole accessibility,
the accessibility of the whole website,
then, of course there could
also be a built-in testing tool
for the whole website.
and please note that we are not
building a new automatic tools
for accessibility testing.
There are many out there and
some of them are really good.
So we are not going to
test if they are good or bad.
It's just: how can they
be combined or included,
or implemented in the authoring tool
or in the content creation phase
so that it supports the
web authors in a better way?
Because what we see is that many
of the testing tools are quite technical.
And they may be very
helpful for developers,
but the web authors are
sometimes not very technical,
so it can't be too…
sort of success-criteria-related and
really technical in the way it's presented.
It needs to support you in another way.
and we think combining it
into the content creation phase
could be really helpful for at least
some of the web authors.
So these are the 10 features
that we are now prototyping
and are going to test.
and these are going to be tests,
like generic tests,
so we have made them
anonymous, so to speak.
So, we are trying to
just test the feature it,
then the prototypes are not supposed
to look like any specific tool, but
but…
it shouldn't be important
which tool you're used to use.
but you should be recognizing
the content-creation…
how it looks when you edit
content. That is the idea.
So, we're doing this testing on a prototype
level, and then, when we have learned
more or less what web authors need or want,
then, we're also going to do test
implementations in the cluster members.
So all the authoring tools
that are working with us in this project
also have the possibility
to test these features
in their own technical
environments, so to speak.
Of course it takes time to implement
these things in authoring tools
and maybe we won't be finishing
this before the project is finished,
but at least we want to make sure that
we have done some test implementations,
so that we can also say that
we know these features work
in at least some of the technical
environments that we have tested,
because that makes it more probable
that they will also be possible
to use for other tool makers.
So the test implementation in the
specific tools is also an important part.
But what we are doing right now is,
first of all, the generic testing.
and because of the pandemic,
we will do some face-to-face
physical testing at our offices,
but most of the testing, so the
quantitative part of it,
will be online.
So it's actually open for anyone
that would like to test these features,
and we are happy to welcome anyone.
We'll come back to that.
So, will this solve all the
accessibility problems of the world?
No, it won't.
But we believe that built-in
accessibility by default in authoring tools
could be an important part of
the solution if we succeed in this.
Because, I mean, this is
kind of obvious, but if you,
if the authoring tool is supporting you
in your content creation phase,
then you can avoid unnecessary mistakes.
And this is really the primary goal here.
Accessibility by default can make it…
We can start with the hygiene factors that
the authoring tools shouldn't
create accessibility problems,
but it should also support the
author in not doing the mistakes.
Another important part here
is really to help the non-experts
to get it right from the start.
Because, as I mentioned before,
most of the web authors in public sector
are not specializing in communication,
and definitely not
specializing in accessibility.
So we also hope that this can mean that the
governments can create framework contracts.
So, in the centralized procurement,
that is very used—much in use
in some of the European member states,
which can mean that tool makers
that do provide accessibility by default
using our features or other services
but in some way can prove that they
do provide good support for web authors,
they can then have an advantage
in the competition
by being, sort of, checked on beforehand
by the central procurement system.
So that is what we're hoping.
That a group of tools
will be, sort of, the front runners here,
and they will then have the
possibility to easier, at least
sell their services to the public sector.
And with that, experts in accessibility,
and also experts in tool making can,
and the web authors themselves
can focus on more interesting things
or more complex issues, and sort
of, solving the rest of the problems
that we can't solve in this problem.
But that is the aim of this project.
So, I would like to invite
you all to make contact us.
and if you are like to—or if one of
your clients or customers would like to try
if you have any web authors,
if you know web authors
that would like—are interested
in trying out these features,
then please do contact us.
There is room for everyone
who wants to contribute to this.
And of course, the more
test persons we have,
from most parts of the world
and with different backgrounds and so on,
the better it will be.
So the results will really depend
on the users who want to test.
We already have
quite a lot of testers.
I think at least over 100 organizations
have said that they would like to
join the testing phase,
but we are always welcoming more.
So please do contact us.
You can use my email, which is
Susanna—S-U-S-A-double-N-A—at funka.com.
We also have a project website.
It's not very active yet because we
don't have so much results yet to show,
but we will be more active in this website
soon, I hope.
So you're also welcome to follow
the project on accessibilitycluster.com.
And with that, I'm open for questions.
Well, thank you very much, Susanna.
We don't have a lot of questions.
We have one main question at this moment.
It is the next one:
you mentioned you will
develop new features.
Do you have examples of what
kind of features are good candidates?
Well, before we start testing them,
we don't know which ones
are the best candidates.
But really it's the test—is the 10
features that I talked about
and showed the slide.
These are the features
that we are now testing.
And if they all turn out not
to work or not to be
of interest for web authors,
then we will have to
come up with new ones,
because we have promised the
European Commission, who is funding this,
that we are going to promote
or provide at least 10 features
when the project is ready.
But as we are just
starting the testing phase,
I can't tell you which one is
the best candidate right now.
We are testing all 10 features,
and then hopefully many of them will be
good enough to present to the world.
And if not, we will have
to make another round
and create new ones.
Cool, thank you very much.
Well, at this moment
we don't have any other questions.
Is there anything that you want
to add on these couple of minutes
that you didn't cover in your presentation?
You have, like, another five minutes
if you have anything,
or we can make a break.
I think I'm—I hope that
people will connect with us.
And I'm happy to answer any question
via email or Twitter,
or just reach out to us and
we will be happy to discuss this more,
because I think there are
a lot of interesting things,
and we are really eager to hear also from
WordPress developers, designers, and users.
And I hope that you will all
be interested in this project
and also reach out to us to learn more.
Awesome. Well, we can give it
a couple of minutes
and see if there is another
question on YouTube.
Okay, we have a question.
Do testers need to be multilingual?
Good question, thank you.
No. The tests will be performed in English,
so you would need to understand
at least the instructions in English,
because the prototypes are in English.
But otherwise, we don't have
any requirements on the testers.
Thank you, Susanna.
Anyone—if anyone has another
question—right here.
I think it's in the middle of
the night in many countries.
Yes, actually, for me it's past midnight.
But what's your time on your country?
It's now 8:30 in the morning,
but it's Saturday,
so I don't think many are up
Yeah, most of Europe people—
Yeah. Still asleep, I think. Yeah.
Just waiting for the Saturday.
But again, thank you very much for
sharing with us and taking your time.
get early and share with us.
I think we're gonna finish on this one.
I think LNN is making a question.
It says, “How much time does it take?”
How much time does it taking testing?
That's another good question.
Well, you can spend as much time
as you like, of course,
but you can test just one feature,
and that will take from five
to, I guess, mostly 10 minutes.
We, of course, hope that
you will test all the features.
and you can also come back, because we
have this iterative process,
so then you can test it again
and see the refinements.
But you can just spend five or 10 minutes
and do one test,
and we will be happy.
And if you are really
interested and keen,
then you can come back
and test all 10 features.
and that will then take maybe
one and a half hours or so.
And you can also come back
and do it more times,
but there's no specific requirement
on time needed.
So you can just do a short one
and see if it's interesting
and then, hopefully, you
will stay on and do more tests.
And then, we have
another question from Ahmed:
if you had to name one thing
that it would be your biggest
achievement in accessibility,
what it will be?
My biggest achievement? Oh.
Well, personally, I think that we
are hiring people with disabilities
in our company.
I think that is the biggest
achievement to me personally.
I believe the key to inclusion is
to have a workplace,
and really, that we have been able
not only to hire people ourselves,
but also help other young people with
disabilities to get into the workforce.
That is what I'm most proud
of in my professional life.
That is not really accessibility as such,
but I think that is my sort of
spontaneous answer to that question.
Awesome, thank you very much.
I think LNN also asked,
for the previous question,
if the time that you described
is also include the training.
Well, there's no training
really here, in the,
I mean, the testing is just
really simple prototypes,
so you are doing the same
thing as you're normally doing as
when you're creating content.
You are writing a text, you are
adding a link, you're adding an image,
and then you are supposed
to add the alt text and so on.
So you are performing
this sort of the user scenario
from the web authoring perspective.
And then there's a really short instruction
on what we want you
to do to perform that test.
So it's not really—I
wouldn't say it's training really.
So it's a short instruction.
Then you perform the test,
and then, that is screen recorded,
so we can see what you do.
So that is sort of fine,
but we also always ask you if you have
any comments or suggestions or anything.
We're really happy if you want
to share with us your thoughts.
So you also have the possibility to
answer some questions afterward,
if you would like to.
But it wouldn't take more than 15
minutes just to do one of the items.
Okay, awesome. I think that's
all the questions that we have.
We're gonna finish the
presentation right here.
Thank you very much for your time.
Just to the people who is
watching this presentation:
don't forget to attend our next talk.
which will be “How to Use ARIA in Forms”
at 7:00 a.m. UTC,
presented by Ryan—Rian Rietveld.
Sorry, my accent. But yeah, thank you
very much, and we'll see you later. Bye!
Bye bye!